Register of the Laurence E. Salisbury Papers, 1916-1973
Hoover Institution Archives
Laurence E. Salisbury Papers,
1916-1973
77032
Salisbury, Laurence E., 1891-1976
4 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes 1.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, reports, and memoranda, relating to American foreign relations with China, Japan, and the Philippines, and to political developments in the United States
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Institute of Pacific Relations. American Council; United States. Dept. of State; Far Eastern Survey; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--United States; China; China--Foreign relations--United States; Japan; Japan--Foreign relations--United States; Philippines; Philippines--Foreign relations--United States; United States--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--China; United States--Foreign relations--Japan; United States--Foreign relations--Philippines; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953; Diplomats--United States
Biographical Note
Laurence E. Salisbury, 1891-1976
1891, March 13 born, Chicago, Illinois
1916 graduated, University of Chicago
1916-17 Instructor in English, Japan
1917-1919 Second Lieutenant, Overseas Service, British Army
1920 Student Interpreter, Japan
1922 Vice-Consul and interpreter, Kobe, Japan
1924-1928 Foreign Service Officer, Japan
1928-1929 State Department, Washington
1930 Assigned to Paris
1931 Assigned to Tokyo
1932 Assigned to State Department, Washington
1933-1938 Assigned to Peking
1938 Assigned to State Department, Washington
1939 First Secretary to Office of High Commissioner, Philippines
1941-1944 Deputy Assistant Chief, Division of Far Eastern Affairs, Washington
1944 Acting Chief, Division of Southwest Pacific Affairs, Washington
1944-1948 Editor, Far Eastern Survey (American Institute of Pacific Relations Publication)
1976 died
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1916-1973. (Box Box No. 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject File, 1931-1973. (Box Box No. 2-3)
  Reports, memoranda, and printed material, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Writings, 1919-1967. (Box Box No. 3-4)
  Lectures, drafts, printed articles, play manuscript, and notes by Laurence Salisbury, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Diaries, 1931-1943. (Box Box No. 4)
  Diary entries for the years 1931, 1934, 1935, and 1943.
- Audio-Visual.
  See photo card catalog.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1916-1973
  - Unidentified, 1945-1973 (Box 1)
  - Abaya, Hernando, 1953-1968
  - Alger Hiss Defense Fund, 1952
  - Atcheson, George, 1943-1947
  - Bales, Col. William L., 1944
  - Blackwood, Wing Commander, 1964
  - Buss, Claude A., 1944-1945
  - Carter, Edward C., 1947
  - Castle, W.R., 1936
  - Caulas, Ricardo, 1941
  - Clubb, O. Edmund, 1961-1964
  - Cousins, Norman, 1949
  - Davies, John n.d.
  - Davis, J.K., 1940-1941
  - Dennett, Raymond, 1944
  - Drumwright, Everett F. (?), 1944
  - Far Eastern Survey, 1948
  - Farley, Miriam S., 1944
  - Field, Frederick V., 1947
  - Fujimura, Nobuo, 1953-1963
  - Gauss, Clarence E., 1945
  - Gonzalez, Gonzalo D., 1948
  - Greene, Katrine R.C., 1949
  - Hamilton, Max, 1941
  - Hiss, Alger, 1948-1950
  - Holland, W.L., 1944-1948
  - Hudson Review, The, 1962
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, 1951
  - Jacobs, J.E., 1940
  - Kahn, E.J., Jr., 1973
  - Kao Tsung-wu [Gao, Zongwu] "Into the Tiger's Den" memoir, original English manuscript,1944-1945
  - Kerr, Jack, 1947-1950
  - Lake, James B., 1950
  - Lane, Clayton, 1949
  - Lattimore, Owen, 1945
  - Lindsay, Michael, 1948
  - Lockwood, William W., 1948
  - McCarran, Senator Pat, 1951
  - McCoy, Commander Melveyn, 1944
  - Mangahas, Federico, 1945
  - Marquardt, Frederic, 1946
  - Marron, Mrs. Cyril Q., 1943-1944
  - May, Gary, 1972
  - Mayer, Col. William, 1944
  - New York Times, 1948-1973
  - New Yorker, The, 1961
  - Reporter, The, 1951
  - Russell, Diarmuid, 1960
  - Sakamishi, Shiro, 1942-1951
  - Salisbury, Mr. and Mrs. (Laurence's parents), 1916-1942
  - Scoon, Mr., 1945
  - Service, Caroline (Mrs. John Stewart?), 1973
  - Service, John Stewart, 1944
  - Sprouse, Phil, 1946-1947
  - Steyne, Alan N., 1945
  - Swope, Gerard, 1951
  - Turner, Bill, 1945 (?)
  - Tydings, Senator Millard, 1950
  - United States. Department of Justice. Alien Enemy Control Unit, 1942
  - Voorhis, Jerry, 1945
  - White, Jimmy, 1951-1952
- Subject File, 1931-1973
  - Abaya, Hernando J. (Box 2)
  - American Institute of Pacific Relations
    - General
      - Correspondence
      - Newspaper clippings
      - Printed material
      - Reports
    - United States Senate Hearings, 1951
  - Asia
  - Atcheson, George
  - Blackwood's Magazine, January, 1962
  - China
  - Civil Affairs Training School - Yale University
  - Dooling, A.B. (?)
  - Gayn, Mark, China Lobby Myths, The Nation, June 5, 1954
  - Hartendorp, A.V.H.
  - Hornbeck, Stanley K.
  - Hiss, Alger
  - Japan
  - Kao Tsung-wu
  - Kohlberg, Alfred
  - Kuramoto, Eimei
  - Kwok Yuk Ming
  - Lattimore, Owen
  - Long, Breckinridge (Box 3)
  - McCarthyism - Newspaper clippings
  - Manchuria - Report of the Commission of Enquiry Appointed by the League of Nations, 1932
  - Manchurian Incident, 1931
  - Mormons
  - Robertson, Walter S.
  - Sayre, Francis B.
  - Tsuneya, Munesuke
  - United States. Department of State.
  - United States Foreign Service
  - Ward, Robert S.
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1967
  - America and the European Revolution,n.d. (by Laurence Salisbury?), 1 typewritten copy. (Box 3)
  - Autobiography, n.d., Typewritten notes.
  - Between Madame Butterfly and the A-Bomb, Blackwood's Magazine, December 1962., 1 printed copy.
  - China policy. Drafted for the Committee on a Democratic Far Eastern policy, December, 1945., 1 typewritten copy.
  - Chinese Coolies and the War, The Saturday Evening Post, October 25, 1919., 1 photocopy.
  - Conquest: A Manuchurian Memoir, Blackwood's Magazine, February, 1965., 1 printed copy.
  - Cross-Currents in the Philippines, co-authored with Bernard Seeman, I.P.R. pamphlets, No. 23. American Council, Institute of Pacific Relations, 1946., 1 printed copy.
  - End of the Frock Coat, The, Foreign Service Journal, June, 1961., 1 printed copy.
  - Foggy Bottom, A play co-authored with Paul Medalie, 1952., 1 typewritten copy.
  - Japan - Notes by Laurence Salisbury, n.d., 1 typewritten copy (Box 4)
  - Lectures - Civil Affairs Training School, Yale University, ca. 1945-1946.
    - India., 1 typewritten copy
    - Japan
      - Titled
        - Buddhism., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Cabinets, 1885-1932., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Communism., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Education., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Emperor., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Japan: 1931-1941., 1 typewritten and handwritten copy.
        - Japanese Army and Navy, The., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Legal System, The., 1 typewritten and handwritten copy.
        - Reactionary Societies., 1 handwritten copy
        - Social Welfare., 1 typewritten and handwritten copy.
        - Tojo and Koiso Cabinets., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Tokugawa Era., 1 typewritten copy
        - Tragedies of Nagasaki, The., 1 typewritten copy
      - Untitled
        - Lecture I., 1 handwritten copy.
        - Lecture II., 2 copies (1 typewritten, 1 carbon)
        - Lecture III., 1 typewritten copy.
        - Lecture IV., 2 typewritten versions
        - Lecture XI., 1 handwritten copy
        - Lecture XII., 1 handwritten copy
      - Miscellaneous notes, parts of lectures, etc.
      - United States - Department of State
  - Letter to the Editor: New York Times,February 26, 1967., 1 printed copy
  - Manchuria, n.d. Partial typewritten manuscript, similar to article entitled Conquest: A Manchurian Memoir, in Blackwood's Magazine, February, 1965
  - Miscellaneous notes, typewritten and handwritten
  - Poem. Farewell on leaving editorship of Far Eastern Survey, 1948
  - Temple Tenant, Blackwood's Magazine, August, 1958., 1 printed copy
  - Ten Thousand-Name Umbrella, The. Blackwood's Magazine, November, 1956., 1 printed copy
  - Untitled notes on trip to Japan, 1958
  - Very Secret Weapon, The, Blackwood's Magazine, July, 1957., 1 printed copy
  - Zaibatsu, The, The Nation, July 14, 1945., 1 printed copy.
- Diaries, 1931-1943
  - Diary entries for the years 1931, 1934, 1935, 1943. (Box 4)